foreign
Welcome to our first episode of the
usata page in 2023 I'm excited to be
joined today by a new guest kelsa
Ferguson who is our health professional
educator specialist Kelso's focus is on
educating Physicians trainers and other
health professionals about anti-doping
that means she oversees the development
and maintenance of usada's Health Pro
Advantage course in collaboration with
Stanford University so we don't talk
about health Pro too often so Kaza can
we start with a basic question what is
health Pro advantage
yeah healthpro Advantage is an
e-learning course that's created for any
physician interacting with athletes and
health professionals in all Fields
including Sports Medicine Mental Health
Care endocrinology and primary care just
to name a few thanks and why is this
course important for health
professionals to take
there are lots of reasons why this
course would be really important for
health professionals to take one reason
is it that by taking this course they
will learn the best ways that they can
support the athletes that they work with
there are really trusted resource to
athletes especially when it comes to
medication use and supplement
recommendations unfortunately we still
get cases where athletes receive
anti-doping rule violations for taking a
supplement that a physician recommended
when they didn't know the risk
associated with supplements or taking a
medication without the proper exemption
health professionals at athlete support
Personnel are also subject to the code
and must comply with the rules and
responsibilities on the code and they
are held liable for seven of the 11
anti-doping rule evaluations and they
should be aware of those
in your work do you find that a lot of
health professionals are surprised that
they're held liable for those
anti-doping rule violations
yeah I think it's important for them to
know and be aware that just like
athletes have rules they have to follow
that they do too and they aren't always
aware of all of their roles and
responsibilities that they play in
anti-doping nice all right so what
information is actually included in the
course
yeah so the course has six different
modules with information that is
specific to health professionals and the
roles that they play in anti-doping so
those modules include anti-doping rules
and responsibilities the sample
collection processed prohibited list
therapeutic use exemptions dietary
supplements and major gains anti-doping
information okay and how is this updated
of course different from the previous
course
yeah so we've taken the time in the past
year to really go through and revamp the
information in the course so it has the
most up-to-date and relevant information
for health professionals who are working
with athletes and we've also changed the
design of the course to make it more
interactive and engaging for
participants so we've included more
animations videos and activities
throughout the course
sounds great so what is the cost of the
course and is it available for
continuing medical education credits
yeah so the course is free for anyone to
take and it's available for a maximum of
2.25 AMA pra category one credits and
it's also eligible for 2.25 category a
hours or CEUs for our athletic trainers
that's great I think we'll wrap it up
there thanks for the update kelsa
awesome thanks for having me here today
and thank you all stay tuned for more
updates in the next episode of the usata
pitch
[Music]